Hello today's דף נ"ו daf is Nun Vav 56, we pick up
by the two dots אמר מר Amar Mar about six lines from
the top. We had a statement about a list of things which
are פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמיים, patur b'dinei adam v'chayav b'dinei
shamayim, exempt from civil from payment, we're talking specifically about compensatory payment
in a civil court, but חייב chayav in heaven, which means that
a person needs to make restitution in order to be good with
God, to be good on a moral plane etc. And the reason
we're bringing it in is one of the cases was somebody who
breaks down a fence and the animal goes out and gets lost.
So you, you know, maybe you're חייב chayav on the fence or
whatever the גמרא gemara said it was a weak fence, but you
didn't directly destroy the animal or injure the animal, but of course
as a result of your actions the owners lost their animals. So
that would be a case where you would technically be exempt, but
obviously there's more responsibility and the reason we're bringing it in is
because our משנה mishna talks about somebody who breaks a fence and
the animal goes out and does damage. And that the משנה mishna
says that in that case they are פטור, patur, they are exempt.
Okay, so now we continue with this list, six lines from the
top. אמר מר, Amar Mar, said the master, meaning let's go back
and look at that ברייתא baraita that we taught. So the other,
so one of them was the breaking of the fence, the other
was putting something in the way of a fire. Then השוכר עדי
שקר, hasocher edei sheker, somebody who hires false witnesses. היכי דמי, Heichi
dami, what's the case? אילימא לנפשיה, Ilei d'lenafshei, if you're hiring them
to come for your, you know, for a case that you're the
litigant of, so as a result of these witnesses that they were
testifying falsely that you hired, you won a case you should have
lost. So ממונא בעי שלומי, mamona ba'i shlumei, then you have to
make restitution. Of course, I mean we might not know that they
were lying and we can't force you, but how could you say
פטור בדיני אדם patur b'dinei adam if it is a type of
a case that were we to know the facts, we would force
you to make restitution.
In a case where you hire עדי שקר edei sheker to say
this is a כהן kohen is a בן גרושה ben grusha or
בן חלוצה ben chalutza and now he can't do that service? No,
no, no, we're talking here about compensatory issues, that's the whole point.
Okay, so it is true that you would be פטור, patur, you'd
be פטור בדיני אדם, patur b'dinei adam, you might escape דיני אדם
dinei adam because we don't know that they're lying, but you have
somebody else's money. So if we knew the facts you'd be חייב
chayav to return it. So the גמרא gemara says אלא בדיני אדם
נמי מיחייב, ella b'dinei adam nami m'chayev, you should be חייב chayav
in דיני אדם. dinei adam. אלא לחבריה. Ella l'chavrei. Okay,
so I hear like Michael and I see he's about to lose
a case to David. So I hire false witnesses to testify on
behalf of Michael against David. So Michael now has David's money that
he shouldn't have. Okay, but I, so Michael has to return it
but I have no, if Michael's escaped and absconded with the funds
and gone off to Hawaii or wherever he is, there's no liability
for me for having done that. I was just like a גרמא,
grama, that you know if I had done it personally I would
have been a גנב gannav if I took your money out of
your pocket and gave it to him, but here I'm just a
גרמא grama and more than I'm just a גרמא grama in general
we sort of speak about how, you know, the witnesses had their
own responsibility of knowing whether they should or should not have done.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says, now there's an interesting תוספות Tosafot but
why we had to give the example that I hired them. What
would be if I didn't hire them, what would be if I
just asked them to testify falsely? Okay, so presumably it will also
be the same פטור בדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמיים. patur b'dinei adam
v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. So תוספות, Tosafot, so if you look at תוספות,
Tosafot, סוף תוספות אלא לחבריה, sof Tosafot ella l'chavrei, תוספות Tosafot says
ודווקא שוכר, v'davka socher,
like four lines down in that אלא לחבריה, ella l'chavrei, he says
ודווקא שוכר, v'davka socher, or specifically talking about I hired them. אבל
אמר, Aval amar, if I just said to them, you know, go
ahead, you know, help out Michael, testify falsely. פטור בדיני שמיים, Patur
b'dinei shamayim, then I don't even have any liability up in heaven.
Like why should somebody listen to me when I tell them to
sin? Okay, assuming that I don't have any type of, you know,
you know, there's no power dynamic there which they're going to listen
to me even if I just request it. Because but if it's
a simple telling them and asking them, okay then that's fully their
responsibility even בדיני שמיים. b'dinei shamayim. דסבר
שלא ישמע לו, D'savar she'lo yishma lo, because I assume they won't
listen to me or
meaning there was nothing compelling them to listen to me. ואין נראה
לומר, V'ein nir'eh lomar, one minute, דנקט שוכר לאשמעינן דאפילו שוכר פטור
בדיני אדם, d'nakat socher l'ashme'inan d'afilu socher patur b'dinei adam, שאין
זה שום חידוש. she'ein zeh shum chidush. Okay, so he says and
don't tell me that the חידוש chidush is to say even if
I hired them I'm still פטור בדיני אדם. patur b'dinei adam. Like
of course I'm פטור בדיני אדם. patur b'dinei adam. Like sadly, the
way the system works is if there's no category of גרמא, grama,
so as long as I didn't do it myself ואין שליח לדבר
עבירה, v'ein shaliach l'dvar aveira, it doesn't matter if I told them,
it doesn't matter if I hired, of course I wasn't the one,
I wasn't the עד זומם, eid zomeim, they were the עדי זוממים,
edei zomemim, I didn't directly do a נזק. nesek. So תוספות Tosafot
says we are saying שוכר socher is not, it's obvious that you're
going to be פטור בדיני אדם patur b'dinei adam and the reason
therefore it says שוכר socher is to tell you that if you
weren't שוכר, socher, if you just asked them you're even פטור בדיני
שמיים patur b'dinei shamayim which raises like interesting questions, right? What is
the level of moral responsibility? But maybe the real question here is
what do we mean when we say חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav b'dinei
shamayim. חייב בדיני שמיים Chayav b'dinei shamayim doesn't just mean that you
did something that was like morally reprehensible. You know, if like if
in the process of doing these things you carried מוקצה muktzah on
שבת, shabbat, you moved מוקצה muktzah on שבת, shabbat, we wouldn't say
חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. that you have to compensate the
person, right? And this even leads into questions, for example, there's a
discussion in the פוסקים Poskim that if you're חייב chayav to me
בדיני שמים bedinei shamayim because you broke the fence in front of
my animal, can I go ahead and seize that property, seize that
money from you? And then the court wouldn't make me pay it
back because anyway you're חייב בדיני שמים. chayav bedinei shamayim. Right, so
the court won't make you pay, but do we say at some
level you really do owe me the money, but we're just not
going to make you pay? Okay, so חייב בדיני שמים chayav bedinei
shamayim does not just mean that you did something that was inappropriate,
wrong, morally, religiously reprehensible. It means that at some sort of philos...
you know sort of deeper level you really do owe me the
money. Okay? And certainly that's the way they look at it up
in heaven. All right, so to get to that level, תוספות Tosafot
is saying, just because I asked people to testify falsely, that doesn't
create that level of responsibility. Like obviously I shouldn't have done it,
but it doesn't make me חייב בדיני שמים. chayav bedinei shamayim. Yes,
Michael?
I just have an issue with the סברא sevara of שאין שומעין
לו. she'ein shomin lo. Oh yeah, I didn't think... you know, but
דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעין? divrei harav vedivrei hatalmid divrei
mi shomin?
Right, I understand, I understand, so I don't think תוספות, Tosafot, that's
why I didn't read תוספות, Tosafot, you assume, if you assume they
wouldn't listen why did you ask? But it means that they had
no reason to listen to you. Okay? Now of course if you're
a highly persuasive type of a person or whatever, right, one wonders,
are there cases of אומר omer that approximate שוכר? socher? Like some
people because of a power differential or because of their persuasiveness or
whatever, they could be at the temptation of their asking, their persuading
could be as great as the temptation of money. So I assume
the answer is yes. But תוספות Tosafot is saying at a certain
point where you don't have a similar dynamic as שוכר, socher, there
would not even be a חיוב בדיני שמים. chiyuv bedinei shamayim. Rabbi
Dov, you had a question?
My question is with... I mean, in this system is that supposed
to be motivational?
What? חייב בדיני שמים? chayav bedinei shamayim? Of course. And it also
means that if you went ahead and did this, I don't know
if it's supposed to be, you know,
then זה הכל, בסדר, כפרה, בדיני שמים. zeh hakol, beseder, kaparah, bedinei
shamayim.
Right, so it depends on how much weight... I mean, in a
religious system hopefully something like this is motivational to get you to
stop or to get you to feel afterwards, people will tell you,
you know, up in heaven, you know, it's coming to יום כיפור,
Yom Kippur, you know, they're still going to hold you responsible until
you've actually paid that guy back. So, yeah. And as I did
say, I believe that you know there are some positions that say
that again, that this חייב בדיני שמים chayav bedinei shamayim could be
enough to say that let's say I seize the money from you,
right? The court won't take you to... you know, take you to...
I won't be able to sue you in court, but if I
on my own just took the money from you, they might not
make me give the money back. So, you know, so that's like
an interesting... the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that, but there is some
positions like that. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so the fourth one is ויודע עדות לחברו ואינו מעיד לו.
veyodea edut lachavero ve'eino meid lo. Somebody who knows... this is the
least, you know, sort of, because it's a... of the... of them,
because this is the most passive, it's a sin of omission, not
commission. You know testimony for somebody that could help them win a
court case,
and you say...
so the גמרא Gemara says, so you... what? עד דכתיב בפירוש? ad
dichtiv beferush? Yeah, well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say. But the interesting thing is that there's some חיוב בדיני שמים
chiyuv bedinei shamayim about what the person lost even though you didn't
do any direct damage, just you didn't come and help them. Like
how about another case? How about let's say, here's a case, let's
say I see, the classic גמרא Gemara about that the מצוה mitzvah
of השבת אבידה hashavat aveidah includes even, you know, even preventing loss.
Let's say I see that some, you know, some car is about
to run over your, whatever it is, your... give me something... your
TV that you left in the middle of the street, okay? And
I can go ahead and grab that TV or stop the car
or grab that TV and get it out of the street, and
I don't. Am I חייב בדיני שמים? chayav bedinei shamayim? Right? I
mean, my passivity caused you to lose money, right? So, I mean,
while we would certainly say presumably I did a wrong thing, presumably
we wouldn't say I'm חייב בדיני שמים chayav bedinei shamayim for the
cost of your TV, right? So why here is being quiet about
testimony any different? Is it because there's some sense here of perversion
of the... of אמת? emet? Like, you know what I mean? Like,
I'm just staying at home, yes, somebody is robbing you in court,
I'm not doing anything about it, but saying like I'm not taking
the TV out of the way of the car. Maybe it's a
case, we'll see, but maybe it's a case where you actually came
and you, you know, subpoenaed me as it were, like you actually
said, I need you to come and testify for me, and I
say, no, I'm not doing it, or whatever, I say I don't
know anything. So maybe there's a little more active thing going on
here. But I do find it surprising if we take חייב בדיני
שמים chayav bedinei shamayim as a serious thing, not just you did
something wrong but like there's real liability in heaven, that the complete
just being passive, you know, and not coming to somebody's aid would
do that. And then there's a lot of other examples of not
coming to somebody's aid. Aid, ha ha. Anyway, so let's read the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay, ויודע עדות לחברו ואינו מעיד לו. veyodea edut lachavero
ve'eino meid lo. That was totally unintentional.
Anyway, ויודע עדות לחברו
ואינו מעיד לו.
veyodea
edut lachavero ve'eino meid lo.
So the גמרא Gemara says, במאי? bemai? would do and not coming
to somebody's aid would do that. And then there's a lot of
other examples of not coming to somebody's aid. So aid, ha ha.
Anyway, so let's read the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, ויודע עדות לחברו. Veyodea
edut lechaveiro. That was totally unintentional. Anyway, ויודע עדות לחברו ואינו מעיד
לו. Veyodea edut lechaveiro ve'eino meid lo. So the גמרא Gemara says,
במאי עסקינן, Bemai askinan, what's the case? אילימא דבי תרי, Eileima debeitrei,
if we're talking that there are two witnesses and they're choosing not
to go to court, so פשיטא, Peshita, of course, you have, now
does that mean liability or of course it's a wrong thing to
do? דאורייתא, De'oraita, it's a פסוק. pasuk. אם לא יגיד ונשא עונו.
Im lo yagid venasa avono. If you don't tell, you will bear
the burden of the sin. So presumably that's talking about somebody whose
testimony could actually, you know, clearly win the case. So it would
be two witnesses. It would be interesting like how can you transgress
something that needs somebody else to be doing the same thing, like,
with you, like you can say, I don't know, he was going
to do it, I don't know, anyway. But okay, but then if
clearly there's, now, what, now the question again that I'm asking is,
is the גמרא Gemara assuming the ונשא עונו venasa avono means that
therefore you have some liability up in heaven for the loss of
money? Is that how it's reading it? Because often this case of
ונשא עונו venasa avono means this is the classic case as Mike
was referring to, is a case where you took a שבועה. shvuah.
Somebody says, come and testify to me about this case and you
say no, I take a שבועה shvuah that I don't know any
testimony. And you're lying, so that case ונשא עונו, venasa avono, you
have to bring a special קרבן שבועת העדות. korban shvuat ha'edut. Okay,
so the ונשא עונו venasa avono there specifically is when that's translated
into taking a שבועה. shvuah. If it didn't, so okay, you transgressed,
but does that mean חייב בדיני שמים? chayav bedinei shamayim? Not so
clear. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says, now, the other thing that's even
not clear is, is, do you learn from this פסוק pasuk an
איסור issur to not testify? Or is this פסוק pasuk only about
swearing falsely? So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says
פשיטא אם לא יגיד, אם תאמר, Peshita im lo yagid, im tomar,
תוספות Tosafot says, היינו דוקא כשעבר שבועתו כדכתיב ושמעה קול אלה. hainu
davka keshe'avar shvuato kich'tiv veshama kol alah. The context of the פסוק
pasuk is that you heard an oath and you swore falsely. ויש
אומרים, Veyesh omrim, תוספות Tosafot says, דהכי קאמר קרא. dehachi ka'amar kra.
כשעובר בדבר שאם לא יגיד היה נושא עון אזי יביא קרבן שבועה.
Keshe'over bedavar she'im lo yagid haya nosei avon az yavi korban shvuah.
That there's a ונשא עונו venasa avono just by not telling. Okay,
but if it was, if that not telling is within the context
of a false oath, then there's a קרבן. korban. But the idea
that there's a ונשא עונו venasa avono is merely from the fact
of the not telling. Okay, so that's number one. That's why the
גמרא Gemara could say you transgress just by not telling. Now תוספות
Tosafot goes on, תוספות Tosafot says, אבל בלא שבועה נמי איכא נשיאות
עון כדמוכח וכו׳ ודוקא, aval belo shvuah nami ika nesiat avon kemochach
etc. vedavka, after the parenthesis, he has another interesting limitation, בבית דין.
beveit din. דכשאומרים איננו
יודעים להעיד שוב אינם יכולים להעיד. Dicheshe'omrim einenu yodeim leha'id shuv einam
yecholim leha'id. Only if you deny in בית דין, beit din, so
by denying, you know, testimony, you're not just saying I'm going to
stay at home, I got the, you know, the Super Bowls on.
You're lying, you're denying that you have testimony. So that might be
more than the passive thing of not taking your TV out of
the way of the car, okay, your iPhone, let's make a better
example, who leaves a TV in the middle of the street? Not
taking your iPhone out of the way of the car, okay, okay,
anyway, okay, you're not just saying I'm lazy, you're actively denying, so
there's something a little more active about like destroying through the lie,
through through destroying that person's property. But תוספות Tosafot says, but that's
only if you do it in court, because then once you say
in court, you're not
even swore in
court, no שבועה, shvuah, you say in court, I do not know
any testimony to this person, then you're not able to retract, because
הלכה היא כיון שהגיד שוב אינו חוזר ומגיד. halacha hi keivan shehigid
shuv eino chozer umagid. So what you have really done is you
have really completely robbed the person of that testimony. But if you
deny outside of court, then תוספות Tosafot says then you could always
come to court later, okay, and by the way, he mightn't say
even maybe even after the court case was finished, right, what, you
know, come to court later, let's say somebody finds witnesses after the
court case was over, they can reopen the case. So it's interesting
for תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says that actually there's no finality to
your act unless you deny it in court and you've never really
caused the guy a loss because you can always change your mind
and come and testify later. All right, so that's the limits that
תוספות Tosafot puts on it, but for us the important point here
is, is that even though the פסוקי psukei are talking about a
שבועה, shvuah, the גמרא Gemara makes it sound that there is a
sense
of like sin and liability and transgression even without the שבועה. shvuah.
Okay, but is that just passively not testifying or is that lying
about it? Is that lying about it out of court, in court?
I'll read you the רמב״ם, Rambam, the רמב״ם Rambam does not have
the qualifications of תוספות. Tosafot. The רמב״ם Rambam in פרק א הלכה
א perek aleph halacha aleph of שבועות Shvuot says, of עדות Edut
says the following. העד
מצווה להעיד בבית דין בכל עדות שיודע.
Ha'ed mitsuva
leha'id beveit din bechol edut sheyodea.
The עד ed has to testify in בית דין beit din with
any testimony he knows, בין בעדות שיחייב בה את חברו בין בעדות
שיזכהו בה, bein be'edut sheychayev bah et chaveiro bein be'edut sheyizakehu bah,
whether it's going to make the person liable, whether it's going to
make the person, you know,
free from
liability, והוא שיתבענו להעיד בדיני ממונות, vehu sheyitba'enu leha'id bedinei mamonot, as
long as, but if it's a civil case, if it's a criminal
case presumably you always have to testify, because anyway there's no litigant,
the state is sort of prosecuting a criminal case. But if it's
a civil case, you're only חייב chayav once you are, the person
says, I need you come and testify for me. שנאמר והוא עד
או ראה או ידע אם לא יגיד ונשא עונו. shene'emar vehu ed
o ra'ah o yada im lo yagid venasa avono. So it's interesting
for תוספות, Tosafot, for the רמב״ם, Rambam, is he doesn't say it's
in court, he doesn't say you lied about it, yet you need
the context that you're actually being demanded to come and testify, okay,
but he also doesn't, but for him just the passive being at
home and refusing to testify, okay, is enough to transgress. transgress. So
here we have the גמרא Gemara saying if you actually are two
witnesses, says the גמרא, Gemara, then clearly you know you're then it's
a פשיטא pshita because you've transgressed refusing to testify. But again I
go back to my question so on A we have the question
about what are the contexts in court, out of court, lying, not
lying, etc. But B we have the question of what does the
גמרא Gemara mean פשיטא? pshita? Have you just transgressed like you've done
a sin, like you've, you know, like you've eaten טרפה treif or
is it that there's some sense of a liability for that up
in heaven? That some the heaven's perspective right, is that, that sounds
like what the גמרא's Gemara saying, that from this פסוק pasuk it
should be פשיטא pshita that the חייב בדיני שמים chayav b'dinei shamayim
is true as well.
Yes. Trying to understand is when does the גמרא Gemara say there's
a קרבן korban for two people who swear or is it even
one person as well?
Even one person as well.
Because it says בי תרי. bei tray.
I know, but that's but that's like it's obvious that there's a
חייב בדיני שמים chayav b'dinei shamayim because you would make the guy
pay. Okay. So I mean when you, you know over in whatever,
the גמרא Gemara discusses the context of קרבן, korban, there are cases
where one person does bring a קרבן korban as well. But the
גמרא Gemara just says פשיטא pshita if it's two people that there
would be a חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. Okay, אלא בחד.
ela b'chad. So it'll be a case of one. So then what's
the חייב בדיני שמים? chayav b'dinei shamayim? So רש״י Rashi says that
because even if it's only one and it wouldn't win the case
all on his own, his presence might have tipped the scales, might
have made the guy admit, the guy wouldn't have wanted to take
a שבועה, shevua, the other person would've had to take a שבועה
shevua and so on. Okay, so fine. Which still raises the question,
so if one guy, is one guy over on the לאו? lav?
It sounds like a person isn't over on the פסוק pasuk but
still is חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim.
Okay, so you also never know, is there another guy?
Right, exactly. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. ותו ליכא? V'su
leka? Is there none other? ואיכא, V'ika, what about the following list?
העושה מלאכה במי חטאת ובפרת
חטאת,
Ha'oseh melacha b'mei
chatas u'parah chatas, פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam
v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. If you do work with the water of the,
that was, you know, drawn to be used for the פרה אדומה,
Parah Adumah,
or with the cow actually of the, the פרה אדומה Parah Adumah
cow actually, so then you make them invalid to be used for
the פרה אדומה. Parah Adumah. It's much bigger deal I assume if
you do מלאכה melacha with the cow than if you just draw
the water and you have to do something with the water, have
to do something drawn new water. But anyway, that's פטור מדיני אדם
וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. Why are you
פטור מדיני אדם? patur midinei adam? Because it's a היזק שאינו ניכר.
hezek she'eino nikkar. It's not visible.
And who you pay? The guy who owned the cow?
Yeah, or the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Okay, but you are פטור
patur because it's a נזק שאינו ניכר. nezek she'eino nikkar. Okay, so
פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam v'chayav b'dinei shamayim.
But still, you made this thing worth from being worth a, you
know, a million dollars, you made it worth a thousand dollars, the
cow. So that's a serious חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. ואיכא,
V'ika, how about הנותן סם המות לפני בהמת חברו, Ha'noten sam maves
lifnei behemat chaveiro, פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam
v'chayav b'dinei shamayim.
That's more similar to the cases we were talking about before. Cases
of גרמא. grama. Most of the cases in our list were sort
of גרמא-type grama of cases. So you put poison before an animal,
the animal eats it and it dies. That's similar to our list
of things that are פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei
adam v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. ואיכא, V'ika, how about השולח את הבערה ביד
חרש שוטה וקטן, hasholei'ach es hab'eira b'yad cheresh shoteh v'katan, פטור מדיני
אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. That's pretty
relevant to our discussion, that's even in our משנה. Mishnah. I mean
our משנה Mishnah says מסר לחרש. masar l'cheresh. Oh no, that was
the משנה Mishnah from where was the מסר לחרש? masar l'cheresh? That
was the previous משנה Mishnah from the previous פרק. perek. Anyway, you
send a torch with a חרש שוטה וקטן. cheresh shoteh v'katan. So
again, you're just a גרמא grama and you're still פטור. patur. Okay,
that's also similar to our list. ואיכא, V'ika, how about המבעית את
חברו. Hamavis es chaveiro. If you scare somebody, you know, and you
didn't technically touch them. So like you yelled in their ear. So
because you didn't touch them technically you weren't a מזיק, mazik, okay,
and they cause them death or you cause them to trip or
something of that
nature, פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני שמים. patur midinei adam v'chayav b'dinei
shamayim. All of these are very similar in that they're cases of
like גרמא, grama, which is pretty much the cases that we had.
ואיכא, V'ika, how about the following? נשבר כדו ברשות הרבים ולא סילקה
נפלה גמלו ולא העמידה. Nishbar kado birshus harabbim v'lo silkah, nafla gemalo
v'lo he'emidah. Remember that?
Your pitcher broke in רשות הרבים reshus harabbim or your camel fell
and you did not make them stand up. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
חייב. chayav. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's a פשיעה peshiya and
you're חייב chayav for damage that they cause. Either because tripping is
a פשיעה peshiya or well that's probably the reason. Okay. וחכמים אומרים,
VeChachamim omrim, and the חכמים Chachamim say, פטור מדיני אדם וחייב בדיני
שמים. patur midinei adam v'chayav b'dinei shamayim. That no, you're פטור מדיני
אדם patur midinei adam because tripping is not a פשיעה, peshiya, you're
not at fault because you left the stuff there because the גמרא
Gemara says it was a case of מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת אונס.
mafkir nezakav l'achar nefilas ones. You were מפקיר mafkir it. Okay, but
you know, you made a mess, you should clean it up. Technically
speaking, you were מפקיר mafkir it a second before, you know, it
became your responsibility to clean it up. Okay, so technically you're פטור,
patur, you weren't a פשיעה peshiya for making it. It wasn't yours
that you had to clean it up after you were מפקיר mafkir
it, but come on, you make a mess you should clean it
up, okay, and somebody got hurt as a result. Okay, so why
not list all of those? So the גמרא Gemara says, אין, in,
yes, מהא איכא טובא, mei'hai ika tuvah, there are a lot, מאי
איכא טובא, mei'ika tuvah, there are a lot of things that are
in that category. הני איצטריכא, Hani itztreicha, but the ones we listed,
there was a special חידוש. chiddush. What was the special חידוש chiddush
in the ones we listed? מהו דתימא, Mah d'teima,
I might have thought דיני שמים נמי לא ליחייב. dinei shamayim nami
lo l'chayav. Ours, like all these things that you're פטור מדיני אדם
patur midinei adam is obvious. I mean it's like surprising and shocking
for somebody who's never learned, you know, נזיקין nezikin in גמרא Gemara
because like, really, you put poison in front
of
your... all of
these are גרמא. grama. So פטור בדיני אדם patur bidinei adam is
pretty obvious. חייב בדיני שמיים chayav bidinei shamayim the גמרא Gemara says
like we're saying, it doesn't just mean you did something morally wrong.
It means like up in heaven they really are holding you accountable
to compensate this guy. Okay, so in that, there's a חידוש chidush
by some of these to go that far. Let's see why one
minute. Okay, נמי nami so the גמרא Gemara says אין, in, מי
איכא תו? mi ika tu? והני איצטריכא ליה, ve-hani itzrichlei, מהו דתימא
בדיני שמיים נמי לא ליחייב? mahu d'teima bidinei shamayim nami lo lechayav?
It doesn't reach the level of חייב בדיני שמיים, chayav bidinei shamayim,
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that it does. Okay, so let's go
through the list. הפורץ גדר בפני בהמת חבירו, haporeitz geder bifnei behemas
chaveiro, מהו דתימא? mahu d'teima? So you broke the fence. כיון דלמיסתר
קאי, keivan d'limister kai, since the fence was getting, it was getting
ready to be knocked down, מה עביד? ma avid? So what, you
didn't do anything, you know? בדיני שמיים נמי לא ליחייב. bidinei shamayim
nami lo lechayav. You're not חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim. קא
משמע לן, kamashma lan, now even though the point is that because
you knocked down the fence, right, you are the animal went out
and escaped. So what do you mean? So big deal, the fence
was about to be knocked down. But you could say, well, maybe
if it was so rickety, I figured the animal would have escaped
anyway. I didn't really contribute to that. Or maybe I just thought
I was doing you a favor, I was getting rid of this
fence that needed to be removed. Okay, anyway, so קא משמע לן
kamashma lan that you can't say that at the time it was
doing some job of protecting the animal and you had no right
to go knock it down. Okay, הכופף קמתו של חבירו hakofeif kamaso
shel chaveiro נמי, nami, putting something in the way of the fire,
which the גמרא Gemara said was the כופף, kofeif, the fire would
have got there with a
רוח שאינה מצויה. ruach she'einah metzuyah. So נמי מהו דתימא? nami mahu
d'teima? אימא דתימא עלימא, ima d'tisav'ar aleima, מי הוה ידענא דתיסתייעא רוח
שאינה מצויה? mi avid yadeinah d'yisav'ar ruach she'einah metzuyah? Who, what was
the chances that this unlikely wind would have come? ובדיני שמיים נמי
לא ליחייב, u-vidinei shamayim nami lo lechayav, and there's no liability up
even up in heaven. קא משמע לן kamashma lan that like,
no, look, if there's a wind coming and then you,
no, that the גמרא Gemara said you're חייב chayav for even בדיני
אדם, bidinei adam, that was the גמרא Gemara earlier if it's a
רוח מצויה. ruach metzuyah.
אם לא, im lo, if
it's a רוח שאינה מצויה ruach she'einah metzuyah that's coming, it's a
רוח מצויה. ruach metzuyah. It doesn't matter. Okay, what do you mean
that it can't be anticipated
now? So therefore the point is like, okay, was it like not
so likely? Fine, it wasn't so likely, but what were you doing
messing around with somebody else's property? Right, it doesn't matter though, it
was only a 5%. You shouldn't be messing with somebody's property and
that's enough to create a at least a, you know, a חייב
בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim. ולרב אשי דאמר נמי טמון, u-lerav Ashi
d'amar nami tamun, according to Rav Ashi that says the case was
that you covered somebody's haystack with like a blanket so the owner
of the fire wouldn't have to pay because you made it טמון.
tamun. So מהו דתימא? mahu d'teima? אימא ד ima d' thought
I the person could say, look, אנא כסויי כסיתיה ניהלך. ana kissuyei
kissiteih nihalach.
Look, I was just trying to help you out, I was trying
to cover it with a blanket in order to protect it. So
I shouldn't have to be חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim. קא
משמע לן kamashma lan that you are. And תוספות Tosafos says one
minute, who the cares what you could have said, 'oh, I was
just trying to help out'. It's חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim.
You know what you thought. God knows what you thought. If you
really were just trying to get the owner of the fire free
from payment, so of course you're חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim.
What do you mean oh I could have said this? So look
at תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos כסויי כסיתיה, kissuyei kissiteih, תוספות Tosafos says
bottom of the page here. ואם תאמר, ve-im tomar, גלוי וידוע לפני
המקום למן נתכוון, galui v'yaduah lifnei hamakom l'man itkavein, אם לטובה אם
לרעה. im l'tovah im l'ra'ah. God knows what you were intending. So
of course if you were intending to hurt the guy, of course
you're חייב בדיני שמיים. chayav bidinei shamayim. What's the חידוש? chidush? ויש
לומר v'yeish lomar says תוספות, Tosafos, דאפילו במתכוון לטובה. d'afilu b'mitkavein l'tovah.
It's not just you're playing dumb and pretending you were trying to
help the owner of the grain. Even if you really were trying
to help the owner of the grain, okay, שלא ימהר לשרוף, shelo
yimaher lishrof, if you thought by covering by a blanket you would
actually prevent the flames from doing it so quickly. ויכול להציל בעל
הבית בתוך כך, ve-yachol l'hatzil ba'al habayis betoch kach, and you figured
that you'd be able to help the guy. מכל מקום בדיני שמיים
חייב. mi-kol makom bidinei shamayim chayav. Why? דאיבעי ליה לאיזדהורי אסקא דעתיה
שלא יבוא לידי הפסד בכך. d'iba'i lei l'izdahorei askei daitei shelo yavo
lidei hefsed b'kach. Because certainly, now here you can't say like when
I put your sheaf in the way of a fire, there you
could say even though it was unlikely, what the heck are you
doing touching my property, right? Leave my property alone. But here you
actually have a מצוה mitzvah to try to help somebody's property that
might be destroyed, right? השבותו לו, hasheivoso lo, and so on, you
know you have a obligation. You see a fire coming and I'm
around, I should be trying to protect your stuff. Yeah, and you
are, and you have a right to, but תוספות Tosafos says that
obligation to protect the stuff does not mean at least בדיני שמיים
bidinei shamayim that
you don't have to exert care. So it's an interesting question, it's
the question of the Good Samaritan law by property as opposed to
by life. Right, do people know what the Good Samaritan law is?
Good Samaritan law does not obligate me to save somebody in danger.
The Good Samaritan law says if I'm jumping in and saving somebody
who's drowning and I take them out of the lake and they
can't sue me now because I broke their leg or their arm
in the process of my saving their life. Okay, I was doing
a good deed, I was trying to help, I cannot, in order
to encourage that obviously or whatever, you have to waive, you can't
I can't have liability in the course of that. What about a
Good Samaritan law by saving property? Okay, I went ahead and I
saw your thing was about to be destroyed and I intervene and
I try to protect it or whatever and as a result I
caused you damage, maybe I even caused you more loss than you
would have suffered or who knows what, right? Some type of a
case here. So would you say, oh well, look, you were trying
to help the guy... or would you say like, no, I'm sorry,
like, you know, you did if you exerted, maybe if you exerted
proper necessary care you would be פטור, patur, but if you wouldn't
have exerted proper care, maybe you'd be חייב. chayav. Now תוספות Tosafot
says you're not חייב בדיני- chayav b'dinei- you're not חייב chayav in
the court, you're חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. But it is
interesting, even though you were doing a good deed. Now the reason
it's only חייב בדיני שמים chayav b'dinei shamayim is because it was
only indirect loss. What if I caused you direct loss? What if
I saw, you know, I don't know, something entering your yard and
it was about to, I don't know, it was about to, somehow
it's afraid that some dog was there eating in your yard, eating
up the grass, and I ran in in order to get the
dog away and in the process I ran over your prize roses,
okay, and I destroyed $1,000 of property? Alright, would you say that
I have to pay you back? I was trying to, you know,
that's not, that's a חייב בדיני- בדיני אדם, chayav b'dinei- b'dinei adam,
that's a direct case of מזיק, mazik, אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad
l'olam, right? So it raises interesting questions whether when I'm in the
process of trying to help you, does that give me an exemption
for damaging? תוספות's Tosafot basic answer is no, it doesn't. Not if
you, certainly not if you could have been more careful than you
were. Okay, and that's, so that's a pretty big חידוש, chidush, yes?
In the case of סם מות? sam mavet? Yeah. Well what are
the parameters of לפני עור? lifnei iver?
What do you mean pre- I mean why isn't that only
the- In other words, if you
know the animal's going to eat- Right, why isn't that more like
the literal לפני עור? lifnei iver? It might be, but that's not
enough to be חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. You know, that's
the חידוש chidush here. When we say חייב בדיני שמים, chayav b'dinei
shamayim, we don't just mean did you do some עבירה aveira or
not? Maybe you did an עבירה. aveira. But חייב בדיני שמים chayav
b'dinei shamayim is, is, are you so responsible that, that in heaven
they hold you liable for re- to compensate the person? Okay, and
that's, so that's a certain higher threshold here of the חייב בדיני
שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. Now you could still say, to me it
seems putting סם מות sam mavet is a pretty- you know what?
You are חייב בדיני שמים. chayav b'dinei shamayim. It did say you're
חייב בדיני שמים, chayav b'dinei shamayim, it's just that you're פטור בדיני
אדם. patur b'dinei adam.
So I don't understand. This guy, like, covers the thing with a
blanket, and we're saying that he's חייב בדיני שמים chayav b'dinei shamayim
because, like, is this a case he knew the טמון tamman is
פטור patur and he's doing it? Meaning, if he really thought he-
this is a pretty obscure law to know the טמון tamman is
פטור.
patur. Okay, so that's a good point. You're right. Like if you
could say, like, if people generally don't know this הלכה halakha that
a טמון tamman is פטור, patur, then you can't say that there
was any negligence. He could have been more careful. You're right, I
would agree with that. That's a good point. Okay, but I think,
again, I think this תוספות Tosafot is so fascinating in terms of
that question of you're trying to help somebody save somebody's property, what
type of a liability do you have, you know, could you have
if you actually cause more damage- more harm than good?
In your case about the roses, I really would be- the owner
wanted it-
If I- if- if you could show that you should have been
more careful, you know, and any normal person would have stopped and
said, okay, the dog is eating some of the grass, but here
are these prize roses, or whatever, if I could show that there
was some degree that you were, like, not careful, then according to
what I think תוספות Tosafot is saying, I think I could definitely
sue you and you'd be- compensate me.
But if you were being careful and just in the process, you
know-
Right, then presumably not, right? Presumably you wouldn't say אדם מועד לעולם
adam muad l'olam if you were trying to act and you really
were careful and, you know, and it was- And
you could also say who asked you?
No, you have a מצוה! mitzvah! You have a מצוה mitzvah to
save somebody's property that's being- that's being damaged, right? That's very different
than just putting a- a sheaf in front of a- in front
of a fire. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says like this, okay,
where are we? Okay, קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. והשוכר עדי שקר נמי,
V'hasocher edei sheker nami, who hires witnesses. מהו דתימא, Mahu d'teima, לימא
דברי הרב ודברי התלמיד דברי מי שומעין. leima divrei harav v'divrei hatalmid
divrei mi shomein. What could I do even if I'm hiring them?
Look, God says don't do it, I say do it, obviously you
should listen to God and I don't even have any חיוב בדיני
שמים. chiyuv b'dinei shamayim. You know, you're, you know, free agents and
that's totally your moral responsibility, not mine. ובדיני שמים נמי לא ליחייב,
Ub'dinei shamayim nami lo leichayev, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that you don't
say that. היודע עדות לחבירו ואינו מעיד לו נמי. Hayodeia eidus lachaveiro
v'eino mei'id lo nami. Now that again, as I said, is the
biggest חידוש chidush in my mind because you're just being totally passive,
unless you
say, like תוספות, Tosafot, you lied and you lied in court. But
anyway, מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might
have thought מי יימר דכי הוינא מסהידנא דהוה מודה? mi yeimar d'chi
havina mistahedna d'havah modeh? There's a case of an עד אחד. ed
echad. So you could say, look, my testimony, who said it would
have made a difference? Even if I'd testified, who said the other
guy would have- would have admitted rather than taking a שבועה? shvua?
דילמא משתבע לשקרא. Deilma mishtava l'shikra. Who knows, he could have sworn
falsely! ובדיני שמים נמי לא ליחייב Ub'dinei shamayim nami lo leichayev and
you also wouldn't be חייב. chayav. קמשמע לן. kamashma lan. Now that's
not such a חידוש chidush because if you're חייב chayav even by
the case of the fire with a רוח שאינה מצויה, ruach she'eina
metzuya, certainly a type of a case like this where your testimony
is relevant, you know, it's a, you know, obviously there, there seems
like there's a good resp- like likelihood that your absence of testifying
could make a difference. But I still would say the big חידוש
chidush here is that you're just being passive unless again we say
that you're, like, actively lying in court like תוספות Tosafot has it.
All right. נפרצה בלילה או שפרצוה ליסטים. Nifretza balayila o shepartzuha listim.
So now we go on to the case of the משנה mishna
that you basically watched, you know, did a good שמירה shmira and
then it- animal broke out at night or it was broken by,
you know, bandits, and you're פטור. patur. So the גמרא gemara says,
by the way, and I want to remind you, why does it
say broken at night? Because even if it's broken in the day,
then you're not פטור, patur, then you should have heard about it.
and done something about it. Or the other thing תוספות Tosafot says,
which I thought is also a nice חידוש, chiddush, is if it's
broken at night, then even if you do hear about it, תוספות
Tosafot says it could be that you're פטור patur because you're not
just through you're not responsible to get out of your bed at
2:00 AM just because your sheep might be grazing in somebody else's
field. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא והוא
שחתרה. Amar Rava vehu shechatra. This case that you're פטור patur is
only if it like dug a tunnel under the wall. Okay? אבל
לא חתרה מאי? Aval lo chatra mai? So the גמרא Gemara says
I don't get it. And if it didn't tunnel under the wall
and it broke through the wall naturally or the wall fell or
whatever, so what would you say? חייב? Chayav? You'd be חייב? chayav?
Why would you be חייב chayav if you did a good שמירה?
shmira? So the גמרא Gemara says היכי דמי? Heichi dami? What's the
case? אילימא בכותל בריא, Ilima bekoseul bari, if it was a strong
wall, כי לא חתרה מאי חייב? ki lo chatra mai chayav? So
let's say it got out some other way. It was a strong
wall, but I don't know, a hurricane knocked it down, or it
was smart enough to jump over it, whatever it was. It was
a good שמירה shmira that you did. Why should it דוקא davka
be פטור patur if it tunneled? Even if it got out another
way you should be... מאי חייב מאי הוה ליה למעבד? mai chayav
mai hava lei lemeevad? What should you have done? אלא בכותל רעועה.
Ela bekoseul reuah. So okay, the case would be that it was
a rickety wall. So if that's true and therefore if it just
walks out, breaks through a rickety wall, you're חייב chayav because you
didn't do a good שמירה. shmira. So if that's why you're חייב
chayav when it just broke through normal, so כי חתרה מאי פטור?
ki chatra mai patur? Why are you exempt when it tunneled? So
תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס? Techilato bipshiah vesofo beones? You started with negligence,
you didn't really protect it well, you only protected it with a
rickety wall, and it happened to be that it broke out through
tunneling when it could have just broken through the wall. Okay fine,
so in the end it was an אונס, ones, but what is
an אונס ones that began with a case that you didn't do
your obligation of שמירה? shmira? So the fact that it happened to
be that it got out through אונס ones is not relevant, you
know, or should not make matter. Your פשיעה pshiah should be enough
to be מחייב mechayev you. הניחא למאן דאמר תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס
פטור. Hani'cha leman de'amar techilato bipshiah vesofo beones patur. Okay fine, that
statement works if you say that something who begins with פשיעה pshiah
but ends with אונס ones you're exempt, I could understand why חתרה
chatra you'd be exempt. Because at the end of the day, the
way it got out was an אונס. ones. אלא למאן דאמר תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס חייב, Ela leman de'amar techilato bipshiah vesofo beones chayav,
but if you say if you start with פשיעה pshiah and it
ends
with אונס ones you're חייב, chayav, so מאי איכא למימר? mai ika
lemeimar? What can you say?
So what that it tunneled out, it could have just walked out.
Yeah, you're thinking because תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, techilato bipshiah vesofo beones
the things are unrelated, you hear this... No, so we don't, we're
going to see and when they're really related, like the אונס ones.
results from the פשיעה, pshiah, then we're going to say כולו חד
פשיעה היא, kulo chad pshiah hee, then everybody would agree. The חידוש
chiddush of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס, techilato bepishia vesofo beones, it's true
they have to be somehow in the same פרשה, like the גמרא
Gemara earlier discussed like if I'm פושע poshea with my well לעניין
גמלים, le'inyan gemalim, but I'm not פושע poshea לעניין שוורים, le'inyan shevarim,
right? But here, your פשיעה pshiah relates to you did not do
what you needed to do to prevent the animal from
getting out, and the animal got out. So that's enough to say
related. Right?
But if the actual way it got out resulted from your פשיעה,
pshiah, then it stops being an אונס. ones. The way it got
out had nothing to do with it. Correct. That's the חידוש chiddush
of תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס. techilato bepishia vesofo beones But it has
to be, you know, your negligence would have allowed the animal to
get out and damage, and that's exactly what happened. So I don't
exactly care what the circumstances of it was. The case where they're
say they're un... that it's so unrelated that it's not the issue
is let's say I said, you know, you were negligent with this
well, you could have allowed camels to fall in. Okay, but in
the end of the day, an ox fell in and you weren't
negligent about that, right? So that's where you can't jump from one
to the other. But when the when the אונס ones results directly
from the פשיעה, pshiah, then that's all פשיעה, pshiah, then everybody agrees.
Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says like this, אלא מתניתין בכותל בריא.
Ela matnisin bekoseul bari. Our משנה Mishna was a strong wall. You're
right. ואפילו לא חתרה. Veafilu lo chatra. And you'd be exempt even
if it didn't dig. However it got out of the full sm...
out of the strong wall, you're an אונס. ones, וכי איתמר דרבא
אסיפא איתמר. Vechi itmar deRava aseifa itmar. Now this is going to
get to your point. So Rava's statement was at the end of
the משנה, Mishna, not about the case that you're פטור, patur, but
the case that you're חייב. chayav. הניחה בחמה, Hini'chah bachama, if you
left the animal even if it was bound up and in a
wall in the middle of the hot sun, like today it's going
to go up 20 degrees, it's like 74 right now, okay, don't
leave... later on it's going to be like 94. Okay, so if
you leave it straight in the hot sun, או שמסרה לחרש שוטה
וקטן o shemasrah lecheresh shoteh vekatan and it went out, you're חייב.
chayav. So so now we're going to focus on the sun case.
אמר רבא ואפילו חתרה. Amar Rava veafilu chatra. Rava says even if
it did something crazy like digging tunneling under the wall, you're still
going to be חייב. chayav. לא מיבעיא היכא דלא חתרה דכולה פשיעה
הוא. Lo mibaya heicha dela chatra dekula pshiah hu. Even if it
didn't dig, if it managed to somehow I don't know break you
know break through the wall or something that you maybe would have
been a more natural thing to expect, that clearly is all one
פשיעה, pshiah, meaning even if it's a strong wall, in the circumstances
of leaving it in the sun, its breaking through the wall is
part of that negligence, because that could be expected, it's going to
be looking for any opportunity to break through. Okay, so something that
normally would have been an אונס is now a פשיעה. pshiah. Okay?
אלא אפילו חתרה נמי, Ela afilu chatra nami, even if it dug,
מהו דתימא הוי תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס mahu de'teima shavei techilato bipshiah
vesofo beones that that would be something that's unrelated
to the פשיעה, pshiah, and that would be a classic תחילתו בפשיעה
techilato bepishia וסופו באונס because just because it's in the sun, what
type of an animal knows how to dig a tunnel? Okay, and
that's seen as unrelated. קא משמע לן דכולה פשיעה היא. Ka mashma
lan dekula pshiah hee. You
see now in these circumstances anything it does, no matter how crazy,
all is part of that initial negligence because that's what an animal's
going to do when it's left in the sun, it's going to
use any type of the כל תכסיסא kol tachsisa here; מאי טעמא?
mai ta'ama? אמר ליה, amar lei, מידע ידעת, mieda yadata, דכיון דשבקתה
בחמה, dekeivan deshavakta bechama, כל תכסיסא kol tachsisa דאית לה למיעבד, deit
la lemievad, עבדה ונפקא, avda venafka, it'll use to get out, it'll
use to break out. Okay, so therefore this is exactly this same
idea that it did result something that otherwise would have been a
total אונס, and even when you left it in the sun you
would say, okay, I can imagine leaving it in the sun it
would do this range of things. Who could have imagined it would
have done this range of things? No, all of that is resulting
from the fact that it's being left in the sun and all
of that is called פשיעה. pishia. Yes. Are we using formal categories
or are we kind of like, as it was just in drama?
What do you mean? No, these are all—no, no, no, this is
a case of did you—where—we're moving beyond חייב בדיני אדם פטור בדיני
שמים פטור בדיני אדם חייב בדיני שמים. chayav bedinei adam patur bedinei
shamayim patur bedinei adam chayav bedinei shamayim. This is a question of
did you do your שמירה shmira to פטור pattur you from שן
ורגל shen varegel when you know the נזק nezek of שן ורגל?
shen varegel? Because if it's גרמא grama and an animal tunnels out
even though you didn't do a good שמירה, shmira, right, there's no
גרמא. grama. I'm not understanding what you're saying. What do you mean
גרמא? grama? It's completely unrelated to your negligence. It's not unrelated. It's
if the animal got out and you left it in the sun—no,
no, no, forget the—by tunnel. Yeah, and you didn't do a good
שמירה. shmira. Right, right, that's what—so that's what he'll say, that's תחילתו
בפשיעה וסופו באונס, that the סופו באונס sofo beones is not related
to the פשיעה, pishia, but but when we come to court, the
argument would be, if let's say you're a שומר shomer or let's
say you are a case of whether your animal damaged. You say,
look, what happened actually was unrelated to my negligence, and I say
to you, I really don't give a hoot, you know, you had
a responsibility to watch my sheep, you weren't responsible, you allowed it
the opportunity to get out and damage, and that's at the end
of the day what happened to it. So if you were negligent
for that result and that result happened, it doesn't matter that you—that
by chance that the way those dots got connected was because the
animal did something crazy, right? It goes back to שמירה. shmira. Yes,
because if you're a שומר shomer then you're—if you are—and that I
think is the key point, right? If you are like an אדם
המזיק, adam hamazik, then תחילתו בפשיעה and, you know, maybe this is
good to help clarify what I said a minute ago to Hillel.
If you're an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik, תחילתו בפשיעה וסופו באונס doesn't
make so much sense, right? Like you can't connect the dots from
what I did wrong to what happened, right? I was negligent but
then it did something weird, so why—why is it considered like I
damaged that object? Right? But we don't start here with a question
of אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. We start here either you're a שומר,
shomer, that's one scenario, you're watching my animal, or you're a שומר
shomer from a different perspective. You have a תורה Torah obligation to
watch your animal to prevent it from going out and causing damage.
So the thing it starts with with is you shirked your responsibility.
You were negligent with your חיוב שמירה. chiyuv shmira. So that's where
it starts. You're right, if it started with is like am I
a מזיק? mazik? Can you connect the dots from my act to
the fact that it got damaged? No. But if the question is
did you shirk your חיוב chiyuv of שמירה, shmira, the answer is
yes. So that's exactly the—that's exactly what the issue is about. Thank
you. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. הוציאוה ליסטים ליסטים
חייבים. Hotziuha listim, listim chayavim. If ליסטים listim take it out, the
ליסטים listim are חייבים. chayavim. By the way, I'm just going to
keep on saying ליסטים listim because that's what everybody says, but the
word is ליסטיס. listis. Okay, it's singular. It's not plural. It's ליסטיס
מזויין, listis mezuyan, it's not ליסטים מזויינים. listim mezuyanim. Okay, but for
I don't know how long, millennia people have been saying ליסטים, listim,
but anyway moving on. What? Yeah, it's Greek. So I'm sure somebody
has here the—you know, we don't have—somebody will look up the Coreen
or whatever tell you what the Greek is. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously if the ליסטים listim took
it out they're חייבים. chayavim. כיון דאפקוה קיימא לה ברשותייהו לכל מילי,
Keivan de'afkuha kaima lah birshuteihu lechol mili, since they took it out
it's considered theirs for all things and therefore they should be liable
for damage that is done. I'm going to go back and look
at that assumption in a minute. But the גמרא Gemara says it's
obvious if somebody steals an animal they become liable for the damage
it creates. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא צריכא דקמו לה באפה.
Lo tzericha, dekamu lah be'apa. They didn't take it out, they didn't
do a technical משיכה, meshicha, they didn't hold it, you know, and
drag it out, but they stood on like on all sides of
it and they forced it to move. You know, sort of like
you stand and you don't let it move in any other direction
except one. So indirectly you're making it move but you didn't actually
move it directly with your hands. Okay, כי הא דאמר רבה אמר
רב מתנה אמר רב: Ki ha de'amar Rabba, amar Rav Mattana, amar
Rav: המעמיד בהמת חבירו על קמת חבירו, Hamamid behemot chaveiro al kamat
chaveiro, if you went and you took, you know, שמעון Shimon went
and he took ראובן's Reuven cow and he put it over, you
know, שמעון's Shimon nice, you know, hay, wheat or whatever, and had
it eat—שמעון's Shimon wheat—wait I'm getting lost. ראובן Reuven took שמעון's Shimon
cow and had it eat שמעון's Shimon wheat. Okay, but it was
שמעון's Shimon cow. חייב. Chayav. You have to pay him back. Now
why? Like given everything we just discussed that should be like a
גרמא grama or something, right? I didn't—I wasn't מזיק בידיים, Mazik Beyadayim,
it wasn't my cow, why am I חייב? chayav? So the גמרא
Gemara says, and listen to where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
It says, and— מני *mani* says גמרא Gemara *Gemara* פשיטא *pshita*, what
if you directly put it over the wheat, of course you're חייב
Chayav *chayav*. Like so like why are you of course חייב chayav
*chayav*, what exactly is the חיוב chiyuv *chiyuv*? And then the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* takes it one step further. לא צריכא דקמה ליה באפיה
*lo tzericha dekama lei be'appa*, fine. You didn't directly stick its head
into the wheat, but you stood in its way and you forced
it and you directed it towards the wheat, and you're still going
to be חייב chayav *chayav* and just like here when the ליסטים
*listim* take it out, they're חייב chayav *chayav* for making it come
out even if they didn't directly take it out. Okay, and so
we'll get back to that, that's a huge חידוש Chiddush *chiddush* and
then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of has a much lesser of
a חידוש chiddush *chiddush*. אמר amar אביי *Amar Abaye*, אביי *Abaye* said
to רב יוסף Rav Yosef *Rav Yosef*: No, הכי אמרת לן *hi
she'amarta lan*, when you first told us that הלכה *halacha*, you told
us that the case was not that you stood in its way
and made it eat the wheat, it's that you hit it with
a stick and you drove it to eat the wheat, ולסטים נמי
דהיששוה *v'listim nami d'hish-shu-ah*, and ליסטים *listim* also when they took it
out, they took it out by hitting it with a stick. So
what's the חידוש chiddush *chiddush* of hitting it with a stick? Is
that much, much less of a חידוש *chiddush* than standing in its
way. Normally the way you קונה *koneh* something is you hold it
and you drag it. If you hit it with a stick, you
made it move but not by directly holding onto it, but at
the end of the day it's still a type of a משיכה
*meshicha*. So according to אביי *Abaye*, let's analyze this גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
because this is a huge גמרא Gemara *Gemara* that says a lot
of חידושים *chiddushim* in a very few lines. According to אביי *Abaye*,
okay, a thief is חייב chayav *chayav* and it becomes responsible for
the animal when they do an act of קנין Kinyan, משיכה *kinyan
meshicha*, and it's not such a חידוש *chiddush* where it's either physically
taking it out or hitting it with a stick, but it's a
classic act of משיכה *meshicha*. If ראובן *Reuven* takes שמעון's *Shimon's* cow
and has it eat שמעון's *Shimon's* grain, so ראובן *Reuven* could be
like a type of a גנב *ganav* of that cow even though
he's not planning presumably to take it and take it home, he's
just trying to cause damage to שמעון *Shimon* by having it eat
the grain, but still you did an act of hitting it with
a stick which is like an act of משיכה *meshicha*, that makes
it enough like yours, so it now sort of becomes your cow
that ate his grain, and you're חייב chayav *chayav* for an act
of שן ורגל Shen Veregel, *shen v'regel*, okay? So what's that according
to אביי *Abaye*, the חידוש *chiddush* is that even if you don't
own an object and even if you're not a שומר Shomer *shomer*
of an object, if you sort of take over possession of an
object through an act of a קנין *kinyan* or even temporarily through
this idea of trying not to take it for yourself but have
it eat the grain, for the purposes of נזקי ממון *nizkei mamon*,
you are seen as the owner of this animal and you have
to pay for its damages. Okay, now that's אביי *Abaye*, at least
there you did a קנין *kinyan*. The much bigger חידוש *chiddush* is
the first statement of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* of רב *Rav*, which
is just standing in its way. You didn't even do a קנין
*kinyan*. What exactly makes you חייב chayav *chayav* there? And you could
read that in one of two ways. You could either say it's
the same idea as אביי *Abaye*, but it's a bigger, it's broadening
it. Even without a קנין *kinyan*, if you basically are controlling somebody's
animal, then for הלכות *halachas* of נזקי ממון *nizkei mamon*, it's your
animal to be liable for its damages. That's probably the easiest thing
to say. Like you could try to even say you become like
a מזיק mazik בידיים beyadayim, *mazik beyadayim*, I'm using your animal to
destroy something, but again from everything we've seen before, like no, that's
like גרמא *grama*, that's very hard to say. So it seems like
from this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* we really have a very big חידוש
*chiddush*, that the what's considered ownership for נזקי ממון *nizkei mamon* is
not necessarily property ownership, not even a שומר Shomer *shomer*, you know,
not even a full גנב *ganav*, even just taking your animal to
have it eat from the grain, you know, not planning to take
it for myself, but any sense of sort of being in possession
of it and being in the position to watch it and to
guard it and taking it away from you and like you know
making it not possible for you to be the one to do
it and now I've sort of stepped in there and so that
now becomes my responsibility to watch and according to even one opinion
even if I didn't do an act of a קנין *kinyan* on
it, it becomes my responsibility and I become חייב *chayav*, which is
really interesting when you go back to like the early question we
asked, right? Remember the early question we asked all along, what is
the basic reason you're חייב *chayav* for these cases like of like
שן ורגל Shen Veregel *shen v'regel* and קרן *keren*? Is it basically
your property damaged, or is it like you sort of damaged in
extension or something of that nature, right? Through your negligence you damaged
and this thing connects you to it, or is it your property?
If you say your property, then becomes the question about well how
do you define what it means by your property? So by the
בור *bor* for example, we've already had a model that if you
dig the well even if you don't own it, it's sort of
like your בור *bor* because you're responsible for it. So here we're
having a similar idea. If you put yourself in a position to
be responsible for it, right, then for these purposes it's considered like
your property. So the difference of the categories start to get, you
know, start to merge because we're not defining property in a very
limited sense, like just being responsible and being negligent and being in
the position to be responsible makes it enough of your property to
be חייב *chayav* as well. Like שמעון *Shimon* and I mean like
the בור *bor* is created. Right, to say the בור *bor* is
your property is less of a חידוש *chiddush* than to say that
me making your cow eat from your grain makes it like my
cow, right? But by the way if you take a look at
תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot*, I want to read like one or two lines
in תוספות Tosfos? *Tosafot* where he says some of these points. Okay,
so the big תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* פשיטא *pshita*, if you look about
eight lines before the lines get wide, it says ויש לומר *v'yesh
lomar* towards the end of the line, okay, line starts with the
word כשמחזירין *kishe'machzirin*. He says, where do we get this idea that
you become liable for the נזק? Nezek No, that makes sense. דכיון
שהוציא מרשות בעלים שהיו חייבין בשמירתה, Dekeevan Shehotzi Mereshus Bealym Shehoyu Chayavin
Bishmirasa, since you took it away from them and they were the
ones that were supposed to be watching it, ואינו יכול לשומרה, Ve'eino
Yachol Leshomra, and you now made it not possible for them to
watch it, לפי שנגזלה מהם, Lefee Shenigzela Mehem, you took it away
from them, יש על הגזלן לשומרה, Yesh Al Hagazlan Leshomra, then for
these purposes it becomes your responsibility to watch it. דלענין נזיקין איקרי
בעלים כל מי שבידו לשומרה, Delinyan Nezikin Ikri Bealym Kol Mee Shebeyado
Leshomra, okay, because it says you don't have to own it, you
don't have to and according to one opinion you don't even have
to do a קנין, just stand in its way, but if you
de facto are in the position to watch it and you've sort
of taken control over it, you are the owners for this purpose.
Okay, so that's basically what תוספות Tosafot says. And by המעמיד בהמת
חבירו Hamaamid Behemas Chaveiro he says, if you take a look at
תוספות המעמיד בהמת חבירו, Tosfos Hamaamid Behemas Chaveiro, he says, ואף על
פי שאין הבהמה שלו חייב מטעם שן ורגל. Ve'af Al Pee She'ein
Habehema Shelo Chayav Mitam Shen Veregel. Okay, you see that תוספות? Tosafot
Yeah, you don't own it, right? You just got in its way
and you made it move and you made his cow move and
eat his grain, it becomes your cow. ואף על גב דכתיב בעירו,
Ve'af Al Gav Dechasiv Be'iro, your animal, כמידי דחשיבא הוא והוא עשה
הוא. Kemidei Dechashiva Hu Vehu Asa Hu. Okay, so since you're the
one that sort of making this whole thing happen, making this נזק
happen, it's considered like your animal. תוספות Tosafos says here's an interesting
נפקא מינה. Nafka Mina. Let's say I made I took Shimon's animal
and I made it eat Shimon's grain בתוך רשות הרבים. Besoch Reshus
Harabim. Would I have to pay? Right, so he says no, because
you're not seen like a מזיק בידיים, you're seen as the owner
of this animal for שן ורגל, and שן ורגל is פטור Patur
in רשות הרבים. Reshus Harabim. So this גמרא Gemara is a big
חידוש on what's considered ownership within this world of ממון המזיק, Mamon
Hamazik, right? And it's basically being in that position even not technically
owning it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues. מסרה לרועה נכנס
הרועה תחתיו. Masra Leroeh Nichnas Haroeh Takhtav. If you gave it over
to the shepherd, the shepherd now becomes responsible. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמרי תחתיו דמאן, Amri Takhtav Deman, who does he take whose
responsibility does he assume? אילימא תחתיו דבעל, Elima Takhtav Debaal, he assumes
the owner's responsibility, which is obviously פשט Pshat of the משנה, Mishna,
דבעל בהמה, Debaal Behema, the owner of the בהמה, Behema, תנינא חדא
זימנא, Tneina Chada Zimna, we already taught in an earlier משנה. Mishna.
מסרה לשומר חנם ולשואל נושא שכר ולשוכר, Masra Leshomer Chinam Ulshoel Nosei
Sachar Ulsocher, if they gave over their animal to a renter or
borrower or guardian, נכנסו תחת הבעלים, Nichnesu Takhas Habaalim, כולם נכנסו תחת
הבעלים, Kulam Nichnesu Takhas Habaalim, they become responsible. So why would you
have to repeat it here? And why do you have to bring
in the fact that he's a shepherd? אלא תחתיו דשומר. Ella Takhtav
Deshomer. So this is a very strange read of the משנה. Mishna.
When it says he gave it to the shepherd, it doesn't mean
the owners gave it to the shepherd, it means a שומר Shomer
gave it to the shepherd. I gave it to a שומר Shomer
and the שומר Shomer gave it to a shepherd, and now it's
the shepherd's responsibility and not the שומר's Shomer responsibility. Okay, so says
the גמרא, Gemara שומר קמא איפטר ליה לגמרי, Shomer Kama Iptar Lei
Legamrei, the first שומר Shomer, walks out. So the גמרא says, לימא
תהוי תיובתא דרבא, Leima Tehavi Tyuvta Derava, let this be a contradiction
to רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא, De'amar Rava, because רבא Rava says שומר
שמסר לשומר חייב, Shomer Shemasar Leshomer Chayav, that if a שומר Shomer
gives it over to a שומר, Shomer he's being negligent because the
owner only wanted him to watch it, and by giving it to
a שומר Shomer he becomes responsible. And here it's saying that the
שומר Shomer can give it over to a shepherd and step out
of the picture. So the גמרא says no, אמר לך רבא, Amar
Lach Rava, רבא Rava will say to you, מאי מסרה לרועה, Mai
Masra Leroeh, when it says giving over to a shepherd, it doesn't
just mean any normal shepherd. It means לברזיליה. Levarzeilei. He gave it
over to his intern, apprentice. Thank you. דאורחיה דרועה לממסר לברזיליה, De'orchei
Deroeh Lemimsar Levarzeilei, it's natural for the shepherd to give it over
to his apprentice. Okay, and therefore it's not really a שומר שמסר
לשומר, Shomer Shemasar Leshomer, that was understood when you accepted responsibility. איכא
דאמרי, Ika De'amri, others say, מדקתני מסרה לרועה, Midekatni Masra Leroeh, since
it says specifically the example of giving it to a shepherd, again
we're assuming it's the שומר Shomer that gave it to a shepherd,
okay, ולא קתני מסרה לאחר, Velo Katni Masra Lacher, and it doesn't
just say you gave it to some third party, שמע מינה מאי
מסרה לרועה, Shma Mina Mai Masra Leroeh, of course what פשט Pshat
in the משנה Mishna means is you gave it to a שומר
shomer and he gave it to a shepherd, meaning his shepherd. מסר
רועה לברזיליה, Masar Roeh Levarzeilei, it means that the shepherd gave it
to his intern, to his apprentice. דאורחיה דרועה לממסר לברזיליה, De'orchei Deroeh
Lemimsar Levarzeilei, that's natural. So meaning that's why it's okay for the
שומר shomer. to give it over, because he gave it over to
a person that was understood he would likely give it to, and
that was implicit in the original contract. אבל לאחר לא, Aval Lacher
Lo, but if you gave it over to a real third party,
then he would not, then he would not step out of the
picture. לימא מסייע ליה לרבא, Leima Mesaya Lei Lerava, let's say this
supports רבא, Rava, דאמר רבא שומר שמסר לשומר חייב, De'amar Rava Shomer
Shemasar Leshomer Chayav, normally you'd be חייב and the only reason it's
different here was a special case of a רועה, Roeh, of a
shepherd giving it to his apprentice. So the גמרא says no, אמרי
לא, Amri Lo, no, דילמא אורחא דמילתא קתני, Dilma Orcha Demilta Katni,
and he's just using a natural case, but really anybody and והוא
הדין לאחר, Vehu Hadin Lacher, it's the same for anybody else. give
it to you, you would be exempt. Okay, so the גמרא has
a strange read of the משנה Mishna that it's not the owner's
giving it to a shepherd, it is a שומר shomer, giving it
to a shepherd, and to discuss this issue of שומר שמסר לשומר.
shomer she-masar le-shomer. Now I just want to raise a question: when
we talk about שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar le-shomer, who are you
חייב to? We would naturally talk... we're normally talking about whether you're
חייב to the original owner. Okay, so חנן Chanan gave me this
animal to watch and I went then and I gave it to
David. So would I be negligent in my responsibility to חנן? Chanan?
And therefore even if some accident occurs to it, or whatever occurs
to it under David's control, חנן Chanan could say to me: You
know, I only wanted you to watch it. You were negligent by
giving it away. You have to repay me. And that's the question
of שומר שמסר לשומר חייב. shomer she-masar le-shomer chayav. So that... but
I have a question. Let's say I gave it... let's say we
say שומר שמסר לשומר חייב. shomer she-masar le-shomer chayav. And I gave
it to David and nothing happened to the animal, but what the
animal does is it goes and it damages somebody else's property, right?
So who does the... the owner of that field whose property just
got eaten up by this sheep, who do they come to? Presumably,
they go to David. David was the one watching it. He was
the one... meaning my חיוב chiyuv for giving it away is a
חיוב chiyuv to you חנן, Chanan, to the owner who entrusted me,
but you're entrusting me in terms of, like, you know, in terms
of protecting it from being damaged. And I'm being irresponsible with its
giving it away. I would question in that case even if I
was חייב to you if it got lost, I would imagine that
everybody would agree that David would be the one that would be
חייב if it went ahead and did damage, because his negligence led
to it being damaged right in some... you know, I could... could
some stranger, the owner of the field, say to me: Hey, you
know, דוב, Dov, if you had been watching it, it wouldn't have
damaged my field. And since חנן Chanan gave it to you to
watch, you're also negligent vis-a-vis me? Right? That I don't know. So
this is the reason I raise... right, this is a context here
of when it goes out and damages. So when the גמרא is
discussing שומר שמסר לשומר, shomer she-masar le-shomer, are they talking about if
it got damaged, which is the classic example and responsibility to the
owner, or are they saying even if I'm negligent, once I'm negligent
to חנן Chanan for protecting his animal by giving it away, I
also become negligent to anybody else in the world who it would
go out and damage? Like I don't know. That would definitely be
a big jump. If the original owner is off though, for sure?
Yeah, because you gave it to a שומר. shomer, Yeah, so you're
off. Yeah. So that... meaning it's... anyway, but that I think is
unclear. פשט pshat we're talking here that the animal got damaged. If
it does damage, I would think it would be very different, but
that's not clear. Okay, let's now get to... now that we're talking
about שומר, shomer we introduce a nice little ש"ס Shas סוגיא, sugya,
which we'll start now and we'll continue tomorrow. איתמר. itmar. Okay, it
was said. שומר אבידה, shomer aveidah, somebody who is watching a lost
object, right? We talked before about hey, I'm just doing a מצוה,
mitzvah, what's my liability when I trample through somebody's rose garden. Let's
say I found your iPhone there on the street and I'm going
ahead and I'm watching it, and then something happens to it and
it gets damaged. Do I become liable to compensate you because I
am watching your iPhone till I can get it back to you?
I'm a שומר, shomer and am I a שומר חנם shomer chinam
or שומר שכר? shomer sachar? So everybody agrees that if I'm really
negligent, I fall below the level of a שמירה shmira of שומר
חנם, shomer chinam, even though I was doing a מצוה. mitzvah. If
I'm really negligent, I have to compensate you. Let's say I'm not
really negligent. Let's say it's like גניבה ואבידה. gneiva va-aveida. I wasn't,
you know, I did a basic level of שמירה. shmira. Will I
still be obligated to compensate you? שומר אבידה. shomer aveidah. רבה Rabba
אמר amar כשומר חנם, ke-shomer chinam, you're like a שומר חנם. shomer
chinam. ורב יוסף ve-Rav Yosef אמר amar כשומר שכר ke-shomer sachar דמי.
dami. You're like a paid שומר shomer. with a higher level of
שמירה. shmira. רבה Rabba אמר amar כשומר חנם ke-shomer chinam דמי. dami.
מאי הנאה מטי ליה? mai hana'ah mati lei? What benefit are you
getting? You're doing it all for free! Like it's a חידוש enough
that you're חייב anything, okay? You're just doing a מצוה mitzvah here.
So you don't have liability beyond the basic level of שמירה. shmira.
רב יוסף Rav Yosef אמר no, כשומר שכר ke-shomer sachar דמי. dami.
You're like a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. בההיא הנאה דלא בעי למיתב
ליה ריפתא לעני, b'hahu hana'ah d'lo ba'ei le-meisav lei rifta le-anya, the
pleasure you get, the benefit you get that you don't have to
give a piece of bread to a poor person, הוי havei כשומר
שכר. ke-shomer sachar. You're a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. What does it
mean you don't have to give a loaf of bread to a
poor person? עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה. osek be-mitzvah patur min ha-mitzvah.
So in the process of taking care of this אבידה, aveidah, somebody
comes knocking on your door and asks for a צדקה tzedakah donation,
an הכנסת כלה, hachnasas kallah, you could say: Don't bother me, I'm
in the middle here being שומר shomer on אבידה. aveidah. So because
you get some benefit out of doing it, you're a שומר שכר.
shomer sachar. Now this leads to a whole big conversation of what
is the scope of עוסק במצוה פטור מן המצוה? osek be-mitzvah patur
min ha-mitzvah? Like תוספות says: What? Because I got an אבידה aveidah
in my house, I don't have to do מצוות? mitzvot? I can
go through that... great! It's a great deal! Let me find an
אבידה, aveidah, put it in my house, I won't have to put
on תפילין tefillin or ציצית tzitzit or דאווען, daven, or I won't
have to go ahead and give any צדקה tzedakah because I'm עוסק
במצוה. osek be-mitzvah. So תוספות says: No, no, no. עוסק במצוה osek
be-mitzvah is only if it's impossible to do both at the same
time. So while I am actually picking up the אבידה, aveidah, bringing
it home, making phone calls, trying to figure out whose it is,
if it's something that's a rug that needs airing out, when I'm
doing things that are about... then I don't have to do other
מצוות mitzvot because then I can't, you know, I can't be doing
two things at the same time. So that's important in terms of
the parameter of עוסק במצוה. osek be-mitzvah. disagree and some ראשונים rishonim
say עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah is
even if you are able to do two at the same time.
But like let's say if I'm walking to do, I'm a שליח
מצווה, shaliach mitzvah, I'm walking to redeem captives, as I'm walking, I
could be saying the שמע, shema, and it won't even slow me
down, okay? I'm there, I'm sitting in the driver's seat, you're driving
the car, I could be saying the שמע shema as we're driving
to redeem captives, okay? You can do both of them. Some would
say you don't have to, עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה, osek bemitzvah
patur min hamitzvah, or you even you shouldn't, עוסק במצווה פטור מן
המצווה. osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah. But the difference is you have
to be עוסק, osek, you have to be actively involved in it.
So if while I am making the phone call I can stick
in my hand in my pocket and give the עני ani some
money, right? Even though I could do both, I'm פטור patur because
I'm actively involved in the מצווה. mitzvah. But just having the אבידה
aveidah in my house doesn't exempt me. Having ציצית, tzitzis, yeah I'm
עוסק במצווה, osek bemitzvah, I've got ציצית tzitzis here on, right? No,
no, no, no, no. You have to be involved and actively, then
you're exempt even if in theory you could do both, okay? But
what רב יוסף Rav Yosef is saying is because there is ways
in which you benefit from being involved in the אבידה, aveidah, you're
like a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. Now תוספות says רבא Rava doesn't
disagree that there's some incidental benefit, like nobody disagrees with the principle
of עוסק במצווה פטור מן המצווה. osek bemitzvah patur min hamitzvah. רבא
Rava just says that doesn't make you a שומר שכר. shomer sachar.
Okay, now why there should be that difference we'll talk about tomorrow.
So there's one other reason given here, but let's stop here and
we'll pick up from this point tomorrow. Oh, I'm actually not going
to be here tomorrow. Oh, so you know what, let me just
say one thing then, because I have to be at a ברית
bris tomorrow, so just give me one more minute so I'll just
tell you like my חידוש on this or my thought about this
and then I'll let let them argue this and take over, which
I'm sure he'll do a great job. So the question is, why
would רבא Rava not consider you a שומר שכר? shomer sachar? So
could be it's so incidental and trivial, it's like not enough money
to be consider yourself a שומר שכר, shomer sachar, but it really
raises a different question, which is why does a שומר שכר shomer
sachar have a higher level of responsibility? Is it the objective reality
you're getting something out of it, so that raises your level, or
is it the implicit contractual obligation? When I say to you, here's
twenty dollars, I want you to watch my thing, there's an act
of a contractual obligation. If you, and with money, the assumption is
you do have to do a high level, but there's no contractual
obligation here. You found my iPhone. Nobody's contracting you to be my
שומר. So even if you get some benefit from it and even
if it's a real significant benefit, you're just watching it because you
have a מצווה mitzvah to return it. And in the absence of
any contractual obligation, could be there's no mechanism for you to be
a שומר שכר. shomer sachar. That raised level of responsibility comes implicitly
because I gave it to you with that understanding, right? But here,
it's one-sided. So that is an interesting question about this type of
one-sided obligatory שמירה, shmirah, are you like a שומר שכר shomer sachar
or שומר חינם? shomer chinam? So we'll continue with this tomorrow. Yes.
How does רבא Rava respond to the second לשון lashon in the
גמרא by רב יוסף Rav Yosef's that it's exactly because God is
the one who? Right, so we didn't read that. So let me,
I'll just read one more line, I'm sorry I've got one more
minute and then I'll let them pick up. So one reason is
because you get benefit and the גמרא says איכא דמפרשי הכי, ika
demafrishei hachi, some explain it this way, רב יוסף אמר כשומר שכר
דמי כיון דרחמנא שעבדיה בעל כרחיה הלכך כשומר שכר דמי. Rav Yosef
amar keshomer sachar dami keivan derachmana shabdei be'al korchei hilkach keshomer sachar
dami. That רב יוסף's reason is why you're like a שומר שכר,
shomer sachar, because if you have a חיוב chiyuv against your will
to return it, so that clearly if the תורה's Torah mandating you,
then presumably it's mandating you to do a high level of שמירה.
shmirah. Okay, of course the response could be no, right? Like why
should I assume that a mandate means, like we discussed before, I
could have a חיוב chiyuv to be שומר my ox and my
well and it's a minimum level of שמירה. shmirah. So they I
get that you have a חיוב from the תורה Torah is I
think two sides of the coin. One way of saying it is
if the תורה's's Torah making the demand, we assume that it's a
serious a high-level demand, and the other way of saying it is
no, if the תורה's's Torah making the demand, it's because another person
isn't making that demand and there's no contractual obligation. And in the
absence of a contractual obligation, maybe there's no mechanism to make you
חייב beyond like the base level. So that's an interesting question about
this type of one-sided obligatory שמירה, shmirah, are you like a שומר
שכר shomer sachar or שומר חינם? shomer chinam? So we'll continue with
this tomorrow.